Guide to the Esther Bridgman Clark Papers, 1891-ca. 1980 (bulk 1914-1968)
Department of Special Collections
Esther Bridgman Clark Papers,
1891-ca. 1980 (bulk 1914-1968)
Special Collections M0578
Clark, Esther Bridgman.
8.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Esther Bridgman Clark, daughter of Arthur B. Clark, Stanford's first art professor, was one of the first women doctors in Palo Alto. She earned her a.b. from Stanford University in 1921 and her M.D. from Stanford University Medical School in 1925. She began her pediatric practice in Palo Alto in 1927 and was a founding partner of the Palo Alto Medical Clinic. She joined the clinical faculty of the Medical School in the 1930s; in 1953 she established the Children's Health Council. She retired from medicine at the age of 72 to pursue interests in travel and photography.
Scope and Content
The bulk of Dr. Clark's papers are her notes, papers, exams, and lab books from course work at Palo Alto Union High School, 1914-17, Stanford University, 1918-21, and Stanford University Medical School, 1921-25; included in these are the records of her research on guinea pig ovaries and the published paper of her results. Other items in the collection include correspondence, notes, speeches, charts, and other records from her medical practice and professional activities, 1923-68; medical pamphlets and handbooks; reprints of articles by Clark and others; personal correspondence; and photographs.
Access Terms
Palo Alto Union High School.; Stanford University. Medical School.; Stanford University--Students.; Medical education.; Pediatrics--Practice.; Photoprints
Container List
- PAUHS Coursework-- English Composition (Box 1, Folder 1)
- PAUHS Coursework-- English, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- PAUHS Coursework-- English, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- PAUHS Coursework-- English, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Notebooks-- English, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- PAUHS Coursework-- History (Box 1, Folder 6)
- PAUHS Coursework-- History, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- PAUHS Coursework-- History, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- PAUHS Coursework-- Economics, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- PAUHS Coursework-- Music (Box 1, Folder 10)
- PAUHS Coursework-- Civics, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Small notebook-- French (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Geometry Notes (Box 1, Folder 13)
- PAUHS Coursework-- General Science, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Notebooks-- Science (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Notebooks-- Chemistry, General Science, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- PAUHS Coursework-- Physics, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- PAUHS Coursework-- Chemistry, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Chemistry 11-A Lab Book, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Smith, A. Laboratory Outline of Elementary Chemistry, annotated. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- PAUHS Coursework-- Physiology, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- PAUHS Coursework--Physiology (Box 2, Folder 6)
- PAUHS Coursework-- Zoology, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Zoology Papers and Drawing, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- PAUHS Coursework-- Misc. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Class notes, 1916-1917, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Papers, Reports, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Theatre Programs, Homework, 1914-1917 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Report Cards, 1915-1918 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Commencement Programs, Misc. Papers (Box 3, Folder 3)
- High school diploma, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Three Textbooks (Box 3, Folder NF)
- Madrono (A literary/social publication of PAUHS), 10/1913-12/1917 (Box 3, Folder NF)
- STANFORD UNIVERSITY UNDERGRADUATE COURSES:
  - Notebooks-- Anatomy (1920) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bluebooks-- Anatomy, Histology (1920) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Notes-- Histology (1920) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Notes-- Anatomy I, Histology (1920) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Anna Franklin, Bluebook-- Histology (1918) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Notes-- Art (1920) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Notes-- Bacteriology (1921) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Notes-- Bacteriology, Pathogenic (1921) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Notes-- Chemistry (1919-1920) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Exams-- Chemistry (1918-1920) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Notebook-- Chemistry (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Notes (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Laboratory Manual of Biological Chemistry (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Notes-- Economics (1918) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Notes, Papers-- English 2 (1918) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Notes-- American Literature (1918) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Exams-- English (1919) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Notes-- English (1920) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Exams-- English 27: Browning (1920) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Notes and Exams-- French (1918) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Notes and Exams-- French (1918-1920) (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Notes-- French (1920) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Notes-- Organic Evolution (1919) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Notes-- Physics 7a (1918) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Notes (1918) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Notebooks-- Physics 7a, 7b (1918-1919) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Notes-- Physics 7b (1919) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Notebook-- Physics 7c (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Notes-- Phsyiological Chemistry (1920) (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Notes-- Physiology (1921) (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Notes-- Physiology Labs (1921) (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Notes-- Physiology 4 (1921) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Notes-- Psychology (1919) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Exams-- Qualitative Analysis (1919) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Notebook-- Quantitative Analysis (1919) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Exam-- Zoology (1919) (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Notes-- Entomology (1918) (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Notes-- Vertebrate Embryology (1918) (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Notes-- Comparative Anatomy of Vertebrates (1918) (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Exam-- Animal Genetics (1920) (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Guides for Vertebrate Dissection (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Notes, misc. (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Notes, misc. science (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Bibliography Cards (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Swimming Records, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - LSJU Panphlets, 1891-1892 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Senior Week Program, 1921 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Kellog, Vernon-- Open Letter to College Seniors (pamphlet) (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Article (ts)-- Observations on the Ova and Ovaries of the Guinea Pig... (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Article (ts, ms)--Observations on the Ova and Ovaries of the Guinea Pig... (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Bibliographic References for Guinea Pig Research (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1922 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Course Registration and Report Cards, 1918-1923 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Exam Results, Board of Medical Examiners, 1925 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- STANFORD UNIVERSITY MEDICAL SCHOOL COURSES:
  - Notebook-- General Medicine (?) (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Notes-- Anatomy (?) (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Notes-- Anatomy I: Histology (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Notes-- Anatomy 6: Neurology (1921) (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Notes-- Anatomy 14 (1922) (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Notes-- Clinical Pathology (1922) (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Notes-- Dermatology (1923-1924),Radiology (1923) (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Notes-- Experimental Medicine (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Notes-- General Pathology Ia (1922) (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Notes-- Guinea Pig Research (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Notes-- Infant Anatomy (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Notes-- Medicine 3,4,5 (1922-1923) (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Notes-- Medicine 6: Kidneys (1922) (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Notes-- Medicine 8,9 (1923) (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Notes-- Medicine 11: Dietics (1923) (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Notes-- Neurology (1922-1923) (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Notes-- Obstetrics (1922-1924) (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Notes-- Osteology (1921) (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Notes-- Pathology I, Lab. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Notes-- Pathology 3 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Notes-- Pediatrics (1922-1923) (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Notes-- Pharmacology (1922-1923) (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Notes-- Pharmacology Ia (1922) (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Notes-- Pharmacology 3 (1922-1923) (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Notes-- Pharmacology 3: Tabulation of Drugs (1922-1923) (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Notes-- Pharmacology 4: Therapeutics (1923) (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Notes-- Physical Diagnosis (1922) (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Notes-- Physical Therapeutics (1923) (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Notes-- Physiology IV (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Notes-- Physiology V (1922) (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Notes-- Physiology V, Lab. (1922) (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Notes-- Physiology V, Lab. experiments (1922) (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Notes-- Psychiatry (1923) (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Notes-- Surgery 1, 2, 3 (1922) (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Notes-- Surgery 4, 5 (1923) (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Notes-- Surgery 9 (1922-1923) (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Notes-- Surgery 216, 219, 220 (1923-1924) (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Notes-- Misc. (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Operations Records, Guinea Pig Research (1921) (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Patient Records, Dep't of Public Health, San Francisco (1923) (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - SF Hospital School of Nursing-- Yearbook (1925) (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - School of Medicine, pamphlet (c. 1920) (Box 12, Folder 4)
- PROFESSIONAL PAPERS:
  - Adoption: Correspondence, 6/27/1946-10/10/1946 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Adoption: Notes, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - American Journal of Diseases of Children, April 1961 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Article by Dr. C. Doxiadis (photocopy) (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Articles, Stanford M.D. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Case Study: Suprarenal Hemorrhage (ts) (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Certificates (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Charts (blank) (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Child Health-- Speech delivered at the White House, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, professional: 1947, 1963. (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence re: Article Case Study: Suprarenal Hemorrhage (6/27/1926-10/14/1926) (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Diets-- San Francisco Hospital (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Files-- Baby Walker (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Files-- Medical Charts (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Files-- Misc. Cases (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Files-- Relationship Between Blood Types and Infant Conditions (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Files-- Skippy (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Files-- Thyroid Cases (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Files-- Ward Reports (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Files-- Misc. Case Reports, Charts, Notes, and Articles (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - First Aid Manuals (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Journal Articles, Periodicals (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Journal Articles, Periodicals (by Clark), reprints (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Journal Articles, Periodicals (by misc. authors), reprints (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Journal Articles, Periodicals (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Journal Articles, Periodicals (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Lecture: Emotional Interaction Between Mother and Infant, O. Spurgeon, M.D. (Los Angeles, 1951) (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Leukemia Research-- Correspondence: 7/27/1949-4/11/1950 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Leukemia Research-- Statistics Received: 7/27/1949-4/1/1950 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Medical Handbooks-- Physician's Descriptive Lists; American Red Cross Textbooks on Elementary Hygiene (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Medical Pamphlets, Misc. (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Notes-- Adapting to Motherhood (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Notes-- American Association of Pediatrics Seminar on Emotional Problems..., 1949.Articles. (Dr. Benjamin Spock) (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Notes-- AAP Seminar on First Five Years of Life, 10/1950 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Notes-- AAP Seminar on Emotional Problems in Children, 10/1952(Dr. Benjamin Spock) (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Notes-- Amino Acids, Nitrogen in Blood (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Notes-- Breast Milk vs. Cow's Milk (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Notes-- Case Histories of Children (photos encl.), 1925-1926 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Notes-- Diarrheas and Salts (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Notes-- The Handicapped Child Conference, Chicago 10/1954 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Notes-- Maternity Conference, 11/1954 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Notes-- Misc. (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Pamphlets on Water, U.S. Dept. of the Interior (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Partnership Agreement, Palo Alto Clinic (sample) (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, Accident Prevention Booth, Los Angeles 1951 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Photographs (X-Rays) (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Stanford Medical Fund (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Ward Manual, San Francisco Hospital (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Women in Medicine (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Oral History Materials (Women in Medicine) (Box 15, Folder 2)
- PERSONAL PAPERS:
  - Account Books: 5/1912-1/31/1919 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Account Books: 1/31/1919-10/1927 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Articles on light, Popular Mechanix (n.d.) (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Class Reunion Materials (Stanford Med. 1925), 1950 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Class Reunion Materials, 1955 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Misc. Booklets (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Ration Books (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Sports Books (c.1920) (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Student-Faculty Reunion Materials (Stanford Med. 1925), 1965 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence-- Incoming: 4/8/1914-12/23/1914 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence-- Incoming: 1/1915-12/21/1915 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence-- Incoming: 2/14/1916-12/28/1917 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: 1/5/1918-6/21/1920, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: 6/28/1927-7/6/1927 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and forms re Clark's sponsorship of Ingrid Klepper, 1941 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, Cyanotypes (personal, n.d.) (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Photographs (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Photographs (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Photographs (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Photographs (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Memorabilia from overseas trip, 1937 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Misc. Personal Papers (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Misc. Papers-- David B. Clark (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Glass X-Ray Plate, E. Clark's Wrist (3/15/1918) (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Glass X-Ray Plate ( n.d.,broken) (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Professional Reference Files (A-I) (Box 18)
  - Professional Reference Files (J-Z) (Box 19)